<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>python on Nihaal</title>
    <link>https://nihaal.me/tags/python/</link>
    <description>Recent content in python on Nihaal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nihaal.me/tags/python/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>FOSSHack 2021</title>
      <link>https://nihaal.me/post/fosshack_2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nihaal.me/post/fosshack_2021/</guid>
      <description>FOSSHack 2021 FOSSHack 2021 is a remote hackathon, organized by FOSSUnited, that happened on 13-14 November. FOSSUnited is a non-profit foundation that seeks to foster more FOSS projects and contributors from India and this hackathon is one such initiative.
The rules were simple: Build a FOSS project or Work on existing FOSS project during the weekend. The projects would be judged based on factors like technical complexity, completeness and utility.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publishing packages to PyPI</title>
      <link>https://nihaal.me/post/publish_to_pypi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nihaal.me/post/publish_to_pypi/</guid>
      <description>The usability of a programming language depends on many factors and one of them is the availability of good libraries to build on. When libraries are available, we also need a way to search and download libraries with ease. Most modern langauges maintain some form of index to make dependency management easier. Examples include Crates.io for Rust and PyPI for Python.
Python Package Index (PyPI) is an index and repository of Python packages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updating vulnerable Python dependencies</title>
      <link>https://nihaal.me/post/updating_vulnerable_python_dependencies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nihaal.me/post/updating_vulnerable_python_dependencies/</guid>
      <description>Finding vulnerable dependencies Safety-db is a database that keeps track of vulnerable python packages and version information. It is updated once a month. They also provide a tool called safety, that checks if the installed packages or packages in requirements.txt are identified as vulnerable using the safety-db.
Install safety
1 pip install safety Use safety to check all packages in the current virtual enviroment
1 safety check Use safety to only check the dependencies listed in requirements.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
